Hello, and welcome, dear viewer.
If you are alive in the year 2021, chances
are you’ve used audio files before.
No, not that kind, the other one.
Think about the different digital audio formats
you know.
There’s WAV, MP3, maybe you also know about
OGG or AAC.
But I want to talk about FLAC, the free lossless
audio codec.
But why should you care?
Well, we’ll get to that later, but here
are my own reasons summarized.
FLAC is an open standard, there’s an open-source
reference implementation, reasonably good
documentation and it has medium implementing
difficulty
There’s not much “easy” information
on FLAC out there
Learning about FLAC gives insight into a lot
of aspects of digital audio, data compression,
and data storage
I have spent at least 2 months rabbit-hole-ing
myself into FLAC and implementing a decoder
from scratch for SerenityOS
First some background on the codec itself.
FLAC was released in 2001, which means it’s
one of the newest of the “first generation”
of compressed audio codecs, eight entire years
later than MP3.
It’s an open standard from beginning to
end and even discourages DRM measures.
Although many of you may have never heard
of it, it holds an important position as being
very fast to decode and therefore suitable
for “weaker” hardware such as embedded
devices or even microcontrollers.
Also, as you will see later, it’s an ideal
format for transcoding CD audio.
So what’s so special about FLAC?
It’s in the name: lossless.
When we talk about file formats, generally
there are three kinds.
The uncompressed are the oldest and simplest
because all they do is store data.
That is your BMP for images, WAV or CDA for
audio, and – wait, there aren’t really
uncompressed formats for video because file
sizes would be ridiculous.
That’s the problem with this approach in
general, even though it’s easy to come up
with such a standard and implement it.
Next, we have compressed lossless formats.
These store all the data that originally existed,
nothing more and nothing less, but take less
space than the original data with clever tricks.
You see, sensible data that we humans produce
and recognize isn’t really random, it has
lots of patterns.
Compression algorithms exploit these patterns
to remove information that can be fully reconstructed.
For example, imagine a piece of English text.
The word “the” would be pretty common,
right?
So what a text compressing format can do is
instead of storing “the” a thousand times,
it just stores: “well, the word “the”
should be at this position, that position,
and these other 998 positions”.
That will take up much less space.
In fact: it’s pretty much what ZIP does.
The same thing can be done with non-text data,
except other, even more clever patterns are
exploited.
This way, we get PNG for images, FLAC for
audio, and Google’s VP9 for video.
You see, here is where FLAC belongs!
But just to finish up, we of course can go
one step further.
Lossy compression starts from the same point
as lossless compression does.
Except this time, we do another trick: Many
high-information types of data, like audio,
video, and images, can be stored at a level
of detail that humans can’t even distinguish.
We can’t hear quiet sounds or small differences
in sound.
We can’t see minor differences in color
or small fluctuations in light.
We can distinguish even less detail in moving
pictures.
So lossy compression just throws away all
the data that a human is unlikely to notice
anyways.
Here, we finally get JPEG for images, MP3
for audio, and H.264 for video, which is the
thing you most likely call MP4.
So FLAC sits in between the uncompressed codecs
and the lossy codecs, as being both compressed
and lossless.
I have been interested in FLAC for quite some
time now, and one time around the beginning
of May, I decided to create a FLAC loader
and decoder for SerenityOS’s LibAudio.
If you haven’t yet heard of the SerenityOS
project, it’s a from-scratch graphical Unix
operating system that is visually based on
90’s user interfaces.
It’s a three-year-old open-source project
in an early state, so there’s a bunch of
work to be done.
Like implementing audio formats.
Anyways, if you want to try out SerenityOS
or even contribute, there are links everywhere.
After having the struggle of my life for two
months, now I understand the FLAC standard
well enough to make these videos.
So that hopefully other people won’t struggle
as much.
Let’s go.
Before we start with anything that is specific
to FLAC, it’s good to have a baseline understanding
of digital audio.
To understand digital audio, we need to understand
audio itself.
You’ve probably already heard this, but
fundamentally, sound is nothing more than
rapidly changing air pressure, created by
natural objects such a string, a resonating
body of air, or much simpler, some fancy stuff
in your body that lets you speak.
When I say rapid changes, I mean between about
20 and 20 thousand changes per second.
These vibrations happen in the pattern of
waves travelling through a medium like air,
one wave is a high point and a low point in
pressure that follow after one another.
How often such a wave is produced is called
its frequency, measured in Hertz.
Higher frequency equals more waves per second.
That’s what humans can hear, more specifically,
that’s what all of this complicated biology
in your ear can decipher into high and low
pitches.
But let’s suppose that you can’t afford
to have a private news speaker whenever you
need them, or even an orchestra at your disposal
whenever you wanna listen to some music.
I know, hard to imagine.
For that, we need to record some audio so
that we can play it back later.
Microphones and the likes can translate air
pressure to electricity, so now we’re in
the electronic realm.
But there are still two major problems with
this signal that’s now expressed in voltage.
Can you guess?
It’s continuous, in time and in gain.
No matter how close you pick two points of
time on the signal, there’s always an infinite
amount of information in between them.
And additionally, the signal’s actual gain
can take any value, at least any value loud
enough and also quiet enough that your microphone
could pick it up.
That’s just what we call an analog electric
audio signal, it’s simply a direct translation
of another analog signal, in this case, the
air pressure.
But this becomes an issue once we want a computer
to talk to the audio world.
The information here is way too much for us
to store in a computer, in fact, it’s an
infinite amount of information!
And as you know, all computers can store is
numbers, finitely many, and those numbers
are also not continuous.
So how do we take this analog signal and turn
it into something we might call digital, something
that a computer can take in, process, store,
transmit, and do all the other fun stuff that
we like to do with data.
The key is that humans are really bad at hearing.
For starters, I already mentioned that we
can’t hear changes in air pressure faster
than a certain point.
20 kHz is actually just an upper limit of
the highest frequency, most adults can’t
hear that anymore.
And second, below a certain threshold , we
can’t discern the loudness of two different
sounds at slightly different volumes.
So what we can do is preserve just enough
information so that a human can’t figure
out the difference between a real and a “fake”
audio signal.
The first step is to remove the time continuity
of the signal, making it discrete in time.
We do that through a process called “sampling”:
At regular intervals, we take note of the
strength of the signal, in our case the voltage,
removing all the information in between . I’ll
not go into the details here, but because
of something called the Nyquist-Shannon sampling
theorem, it is mathematically proven that
we can recreate any frequency that is sampled
at least twice per oscillation , meaning that
if the highest necessary frequency has 20,000
oscillations per second, we need to sample
it 40,000 times per second.
The term “Hertz” for describing how often
something happens per second is also used
for sampling, so for this, we would say a
“sampling rate” of 40 kHz.
You might have heard of the sampling rates
44.1 kHz or 48 kHz.
Those are the most common ones and the reason
that they’re higher than 40 kHz is unfortunately
not something I can go into today .
And second, we need to remove the remaining
value continuity of these sample points.
That’s called quantization . We translate
these voltages into whole numbers , where
the lowest number represents the lowest signal
strength and the highest number the highest
signal strength.
Now, how many numbers do we need here?
The critical question is again; at what point
can a human no longer hear the difference
in volume?
If we had six different values, we could have
three different volumes for an audio wave.
That’s almost a difference between 30% and
70% volume, and you can clearly hear that.
But it turns out that once we reach about
50,000 different volumes for signals, the
human hearing stops noticing a difference.
We call whatever amount of different values
we allow our “bit depth”.
Because in reality these numbers will all
be stored in binary by the computer, so it
makes sense that the range in values is a
power of two.
By the bit depth, we don’t directly mean
the number of possible values, like 65,536,
we instead mean the number of bits we use
to store one such sample value, like 16.
As I’ve already said, a bit depth of 16
is about at the limit of what humans can hear,
so bit depths below that are uncommon, but
above it are sometimes seen.
So let’s revisit that.
What we have now is a list of numbers, each
representing the strength of an audio signal
at some point in time, with all these points
in time regularly spaced according to a sample
rate.
The bit rate of the numbers tells us the maximum
and minimum values, which represent the real-world
maximum and minimum pressure or voltage.
This is called pulse code modulation, PCM,
and it’s by far the most important way of
digitizing any signal, not just audio.
There are variations we can do here [non-linear
quantization, dynamic sample rates], but remember
that this is all because circuits, real digital-analog
electronic hardware components, can do these
conversions super easily and accurately, both
going from analog to digital, and from digital
to analog.
And unfortunately for you, the early viewer,
this is where I’ll end the first video of
the FLAC series.
I’m planning to cover every single part
of the specification, including, what you
saw today, all the audio fundamentals you’ll
have to know.
In episode 2, we’ll have a look at how we
can losslessly compress the audio data we
have now obtained, and in episode 3, we’ll
peek inside how FLAC stores all of this stuff.