Hello and welcome, dear viewer, to the second
video in the three-part FLAC series.
Today, I’m actually concerning myself with
what makes FLAC tick, and how it does its
compression.
Note that the first video, you can watch that
up here, was just an introduction to digital
audio, so if you haven’t seen it and you
know all of these terms, you should be good.
Last time, we saw how we can take a sound
wave and represent it literally with numbers,
which is called Pulse Code Modulation.
If you want to go the short route for storing
the audio data, you can of course take these
PCM samples and throw them into your file
as-is.
If you did that, you would get the WAV format.
But as I mentioned in the first video, the
file sizes here get large fast.
Simple math tells us that there are about
1.4 megabits of sample data for each second.
However, FLAC can commonly compress this to
about half the size, 600 kilobits per second
or even less.
We can go further and reach for 150 kilobits
with MP3, but we’re here for lossless compression.
Today I want to dig deep, so it’s easy to
lose track of what we’re trying to do, and
what we have done so far.
Therefore, let’s look at this sidebar once
in a while, just to keep the big picture in
mind.
Linear Predictive Coding
The
key to all kinds of compression is patterns.
Last time, I demonstrated how repeats in data
can be easily removed with basic compression.
Now, if you were to look at this audio data,
there’s no obvious repetition here.
But remember that no matter how random this
looks, we’re still dealing with sound.
And sound is made up of waves, whose defining
feature is that they repeat.
But what are these waves, actually?
I didn’t mention it in the last episode
because it wasn’t relevant, but the most
basic kind of wave is a sine wave.
The mathematical function takes parameters
that modify the amplitude, frequency, phase
and offset of the wave.
In fact, it’s the case that any sound can
be described just by the basic sine waves
it is made out of.
Now you might have a first idea of how to
store the samples: Check what sine waves constitute
this signal, then just store those sine waves
and their parameters.
That’s a great idea, in fact, you’re about
to reinvent MP3 and the Discrete Sine Transform.
But for FLAC, we won’t see much of a benefit.
The number of frequencies we need to store
is extremely large.
It’s so large that we need just as much
data as for the samples themselves.
And, sine waves are rather expensive to compute.
So let’s use something simpler.
How about a polynomial function?
A quick refresher on high school calculus:
A monomial is any function like these, where
the parameter x is taken to an integer power
and multiplied by a coefficient, and a polynomial
is just adding a bunch of monomials.
Linear functions, constant functions or quadratic
functions, they’re all polynomials.
If we consider the coefficients again, there’s
only one coefficient per x term.
So a function of degree 5, meaning 5 is the
highest power of x, can only have 6 coefficients.
Don’t forget x^0, the constant term!
But we need to take a step back.
We want to approximate waves, which are sine
functions.
Polynomials are nothing like sine functions,
at least not out of the box.
Some of you are already guessing where I’m
going with this, so let me tell you about
one of the most amazing things in calculus.
Like sine itself, on the one hand we have
a lot of weird functions in math.
On the other hand, we have the super-simple
polynomial functions.
So how about we approximate a complicated
function, any function, with a polynomial?
For starters, we pick a point x0 on the function
where the approximation is “centered”,
so to speak.
Then, our approximated function T should of
course have the same value as the original
function at this point.
And then, T should probably have the same
derivative in x0 as f does, so that its slope
is the same.
And then, T should probably have the same
second derivative in x0 as f does, so that
its curve is the same.
And so on, as long as you want to.
If you’re curious about how we get this
formula, watch the linked video, I don’t
have time right now.
The gist is that especially for functions
that can be derived a lot, the approximation
with a polynomial is really good.
In the case of sine and cosine, in fact, arbitrarily
good!
These formulas here is just what we get when
we put in the well-known values and derivatives
of sine and cosine.
The function T we just created is called the
Taylor Series of f, and it’s one of the
most powerful numeric tools in existence.
In our case, we just need to know this: It’s
very possible to approximate an audio wave
closely with a polynomial.
[sidebar: idea 2]
But, I have again kind of lied to you.
Sure, we can approximate the audio wave with
a polynomial, and we can tune how close we
get by choosing what degree the polynomial
is.
But this kind of approximation breaks down
very fast with more than a handful of samples.
The required polynomial degrees would be extremely
large, which is expensive and unstable on
all fronts.
Let’s try to improve things.
I kind of skipped over it, but we’re of
course not in discrete real number math land.
All our numbers are discrete and finite, both
in x and y.
This means that we’re not dealing with approximating
a function with a function, we’re approximating
a series with a series, or rather, a digital
signal with a digital signal.
As long as we keep our signal defined like
this, however, we’re just switching up the
notation, nothing actually changes, practically
speaking.
The magic only happens once we use a recursive
definition [sidebar: idea 3].
You might have heard about recursion before
[google joke], and here we just mean that
we define a signal’s value as a combination
of previous signal values.
Recursion is not super common in the kind
of calculus you learn in school, but it turns
out to be a powerful tool for data compression.
Now, you have to briefly take my word and
believe me that these specific recursive signal
definitions are really great.
What does this notation mean?
The sample at position t is specified to be
two times the sample at position t-1 minus
the sample at position t-2.
Therefore, if we already know the previous
samples, we can compute the next sample very
easily.
But what if we don’t yet know the previous
samples?
That’s a problem all recursive definitions
need to solve, there has to be a non-recursive
starting point.
More formally, there is an infinite number
of non-recursive functions that fulfil this
recursive formula.
We take the easiest way out and say that the
first couple of samples have some constant
values.
How many constants samples simply depends
on how many previous samples our formula asks
for.
So let’s revisit the procedure and introduce
some terminology.
Out of the four different orders, we are given
one predictor as well as the warm-up samples.
The order specifies how many samples we need
to look back, so how many constant warm-up
samples we need.
For the first couple of samples, we don’t
use the recursive predictor formula, only
afterwards.
Not only is this extremely cheap to compute,
it’s also super space-efficient.
Because there’s only one predictor per order,
we just store the order instead of the coefficients
themselves.
And at the same time, the order tells us how
many warm-up samples there are.
What we’re doing here is encoding samples
by predicting what the next sample will be,
based on a linear combination of the previous
samples.
That’s why we call it Linear Predictive
Coding.
You remember how you took my word a minute
ago when I said that you have to believe in
the greatness of these specific predictors?
Well, let’s get to why that is.
LPC does not always result in polynomial functions,
in fact, most of the time it doesn’t.
And even though it doesn’t look like it
from the seemingly arbitrary coefficients,
these predictors here are the only ones of
their order that do actually correspond to
a polynomial function.
It’s not magic, it’s math.
Let’s look at this from another angle.
We have a number of samples that were already
decoded, and we now want to predict what the
next sample will be.
How can we do that?
Let’s take the simplest approach first and
try to use a line.
In math, of course, we call that a linear
function, or a polynomial of degree 1.
So we want to insert a line somewhere here,
and the prediction we make is where the line
intersects the sample’s point in time, which
we called t.
A linear function consists of only two parameters:
the slope and the vertical position; but we
want to recursively define them depending
on the previous samples.
First, let’s ignore the slope.
I challenge you to come up with a position
for the sample t.
[pause] Your solution is probably too complicated.
Let’s do this as simple as possible and
use the previous sample.
We can think of the previous sample as our
starting point, just something to go off from.
Now what about the slope?
Think about what we just did with the position,
we simply copied it.
So how about we copy the slope too?
The best slope to use of course is the slope
between the previous two samples.
If you took any amount of calculus, you know
that this slope can be calculated by dividing
the y difference by the x difference.
Lucky for us, the x difference is 1 and the
y difference is the difference between these
two samples.
Now, shifting this slope triangle to the right
so that it starts at the previous sample shows
us where we predict the next sample to be.
In terms of our formula, we add the slope
to the position.
And that’s already the second order predictor!
Note that the very last step only works because
all the samples have the same distance, so
the x portion of the slope triangle is always
1.
This assumption of a distance of 1 is one
we generally make because it doesn’t really
change anything but it simplifies the math.
Now that you have seen how we can come up
with a formula for the simple case, let me
show you a more formal mathematical method.
This is less intuitive, but more robust, as
we can use it for even the very highest predictor
orders.
Our starting point again are the Taylor polynomials.
Remember, the fundamental assumption behind
Taylor is that we can approximate some unknown
input by adding up the function and its derivatives
at a known input.
For the best accuracy, let’s pick the last
decoded sample as our known input.
For the function’s value itself, that’s
of course just this sample, but we don’t
even know the first derivative!
After all, we don’t actually know the underlying
function, we can’t derive it with calculus.
Instead, we have to approximate the derivative
as well, and we’re gonna use Taylor once
more.
First, we need to decide how many samples
we want to use to approximate the derivative.
You can use arbitrarily many, and for reasons
outside the scope here, that will give you
better and better approximations.
However, just know that we need at least two
samples for the first derivative, at least
three samples for the second derivative, and
so on.
So for us, let’s just choose the sample
at t-1 which we’re dealing with anyways,
and the one before that, t-2.
To make it simple, our assumption will be
that we can calculate the discrete derivative
at t-1 by some linear combination of the know
samples at t-1 and t-2.
Alright, and this might seem arbitrary at
first, let’s write both those samples not
as the actual value they are, but how we could
in theory calculate them by a Taylor approximation
from t-1.
And then let’s plug that into the right
side of the linear combination.
Do you see now?
If I write the left-hand side more explicitly
and rearrange the right side, it might be
a bit more obvious.
We have coefficients for both the sample and
its derivative on both sides.
That means in order for this formula to be
correct, all the corresponding coefficients
need to be equal, and that gives us a linear
system of equations containing a and b as
the unknowns.
Luckily, this system is super easy to solve,
and we get a=1 and b=-1.
Plug that back into the very first equation
and we have an approximation for the derivative.
Not too bad, was it?
Of course, the steps quickly get out of hand
once we try the same thing for higher-order
derivatives.
However, the procedure is exactly the same,
you just have longer expansions and more equations
in the system.
I encourage you to try doing the second derivative
yourself.
Remember, we need the previous three samples,
and if you know a thing or two about linear
systems of equations, you should be able to
tell why that is.
Finally, we need to invoke Taylor once more
and just combine these derivatives into one
formula for the sample we actually care about.
There’s a tradeoff here: Using more derivatives
gives us a better approximation, that’s
just a basic property of Taylor polynomials.
On the other hand, higher derivatives require
more samples and more time to compute.
So depending on how much accuracy we need,
we can select zero to three derivatives, and
simplifying these equations gives us exactly
the five predictors we know from before.
Of course, if you’ve been calculating the
Taylor expansions along at home, these formulas
aren’t correct, some of the higher derivatives
are missing a factor.
That is indeed intentional, we’re not doing
exact math, we’re just trying to do some
sample prediction to compress audio.
Avoiding the factorial divisors makes this
entire thing cheaper to compute, which – you
remember – was the whole point of linear
predictive coding.
Two remarks before we continue: First, it
is important to remember that this whole polynomial
prediction business only applies at the level
of the few previous samples.
We’re not, in fact, trying to approximate
all of the samples with just one polynomial,
that’s never a good idea.
And second, in general, when we’re talking
about linear predictive coding, the coefficients
here can be anything.
The resulting function is then not a polynomial
anymore, but it turns out that many of them
are even better at signal prediction than
the five simple ones we initially looked at.
So of course FLAC supports them, the highest
order we can go to is 32.
I have to mention though that this is extremely
computationally intensive, especially for
encoding.
Choosing predictor order and coefficients
for arbitrary LPC involves just way too much
linear algebra.
On the other hand, the polynomial predictors
are so cheap that you can just encode with
all five of them and pick the one that compresses
best.
Now, remember that LPC contains the word “predictive”.
It’s predicting the sample values, not exactly
reproducing them.
This means that no matter how hard we try,
there will always be an error.
If we subtract the predicted signal from the
actual signal, we get something called the
residual.
A list of numbers, once again.
You might say now that all this linear predictive
coding didn’t gain us much if we’re still
left with these numbers that need to be included.
Remember: it’s lossless.
At this point we could invent the Free Lossy
Audio Codec and throw away most of the information.
But that’s not today’s topic, we need
all of the data here.
Recall that in the previous step, we didn’t
store separate data for most samples.
Well, that turns out to not work very well
here; I’ll go ahead and assume that we need
to store all residuals independent of each
other.
The first idea would of course be to pick
a bit depth, probably something similar to
the original bit depth, and just encode the
residuals with that.
And we’re not totally off base here!
FLAC allows you to go that route if everything
else fails.
You have to be careful with what bit depth
you choose, as all the residuals have to fit,
but it’s totally possible!
Though as the astute among you have already
noticed, this is super inefficient.
Let’s think of a very simple but common
scenario.
We have a very good approximation of our original
samples, so all of our residuals are really
small in magnitude, like plus or minus 32
at maximum.
But there are these few samples towards the
end that do not fit our curve at all, and
their residual size is ridiculously large,
like a couple thousand.
So, just to fit those few outliers, we immediately
need a bit depth of say 10 to 12.
Which wastes a lot of bits on the small numbers.
An insight we need here is some information
theory fundamentals.
3blue1brown made an excellent video on the
matter, so I’ll keep it brief.
What I implicitly already told you is a very
important observation about the residual data:
Because they are residuals from a function
approximation, most values are pretty small.
To put it another way: If you are reading
through the list of residuals at random, the
probability of hitting any specific value
is not equal: you are more likely to find
small values than large values.
So for an encoding scheme to use the least
amount of bits, it should use very little
space to store common, small values, and it
can be allowed to use a bit of excessive space
for uncommon, large values.
As I said, a constant bit depth is out.
How about a variable bit depth?
If we can specify how many bits a number uses,
we can choose lower bit depths for smaller
numbers and larger bit depths for larger numbers.
So let’s have two numbers: one specifies
the bit depth and the other is the encoded
value itself at that bit depth.
This sounds like a good idea but it’s not
efficient.
We have only moved our problem because now
we need to pick and choose another bit depth
for the bit depth specifier!
Our maximum bit depth still needs to support
the very large bit depths for very large numbers.
All in all, we don’t gain much.
The bit depth specifier needs to have a variable
size as well.
The simplest method is to use unary encoding.
In unary, a number is simply represented by
the number of symbols that are present.
Tally marks.
In computers, which only store binary, we
need a terminating symbol, so we use zeroes
followed by a single one.
And yes, that means that there is one symbol
more than the number we store, this is intentional
and will come in handy later.
Getting back to the encoding, we can then
place the number itself after that.
Except all numbers start with a 1 in binary,
so we don’t need to store that 1 again.
The unary-encoded bit depth can then be thought
of as the highest power of two that the number
contains.
So to encode: count the number of bits in
the value and store that many zeroes.
Then, store the number itself, starting with
the highest 1 bit.
To decode: Read zeroes until you hit a 1,
then keep reading afterwards as many bits
as there were zeroes.
The decoded value is this second half as well
as the leading 1.
This encoding scheme is known as Elias gamma
coding [sidebar: idea 5], and it’s already
great!
I mean, it’s good enough for Pokémon Gen
1 sprites.
But we still have two major drawbacks that
need fixing: First: gamma coding can’t encode
a zero.
This is easy enough to fix: we just add 1
to the number before encoding it and subtract
that 1 after decoding.
This method has its own name, the Exponential
Golomb code.
Second, however, the encoded size is a problem.
We can encode arbitrarily-sized numbers with
gamma coding, but the number of required bits
always doubles!
Small numbers don’t mind, but large numbers
do.
So here’s the procedure.
We pick a parameter k, which is called the
order of the Exponential Golomb code.
Order 0 will give us what we previously discussed,
and higher orders give us better encoding
of larger numbers but worse encoding of smaller
numbers.
We’re encoding any number now as a multiple
of a base plus a remainder.
Our base is always the kth power of 2, that’s
the “exponential” part.
The great thing is that in binary, multiplying
or dividing by a power of two is just shifting
bits around.
So by splitting the number up into a multiple
of a power of two plus a remainder when dividing
by that power of two, we just literally split
the bits of the number into two parts.
We encode the quotient with order 0 Exponential
Golomb coding, which is just what we discussed
beforehand, with the unary and stuff.
Then, afterwards, we just append the remainder,
which of course always uses k bits.
When I first understood this coding, it was
magical.
Let’s take a moment to appreciate what this
is doing.
We’re still making use of all the efficient
fun stuff, like variable bit depth for arbitrarily
large numbers.
But the k gives us a fixed number of lower
bits that are included as-is, while we perform
Exponential Golomb on the upper, more significant
bits.
Critically, we don’t increase the bit count
by 2 when we double the number, as the lower
bits have nothing to do with the coding of
the upper bits.
As we increase k, we get larger numbers of
fixed low bits, which are quite expensive
for small numbers.
But for larger numbers, the encoding of the
upper bits allows us to reach ridiculous values
without the double cost from before.
Again, we can now pick the tradeoff.
If our residuals are good and we only have
a few large numbers, we choose k very small
or even 0, leading to very good small number
compression.
If our residuals are bad, we choose a larger
k and can still compress data while not paying
double the price for large numbers.
FLAC recognizes that even within a single
list of residuals, there are many different
collections of residuals that need differing
treatment.
So you can actually choose up to a sequence
of 32,768 different orders for a single residual
list!
And if any chunk of residuals compresses badly,
you just don’t compress it.
The observant viewers might have noticed that
we still have a problem.
All the numbers that Exponential Golomb can
encode are positive, but residuals, as all
audio data, are signed, so both positive and
negative.
It’s a similar situation to how we didn’t
have zero in Elias gamma coding.
But again, there’s a simple fix.
If we just store positive and negative numbers
alternatingly, we can make numbers of small
magnitude map to few bits and keep our good
properties.
More specifically, we map non-positive x to
-2x and positive x to 2x-1.
Let’s take a step back and look at the bigger
picture.
So far, we have only concerned ourselves with
one stream of audio, one list of samples,
and one channel.
But the reality is that most audio has at
least two channels, stereo of course.
And it would be really wasteful to just encode
both channels independently!
After all, most stereo audio has very similar
or even the same audio on both the left and
right channels.
So what we can do instead is Interchannel
Decorrelation.
Instead of a left and right channel, we use
a mid and side channel.
The mid channel stores the average of the
two channels, while the side channel stores
the difference between the channels.
To decode, we just use mid+side for the left
channel and mid-side for the right channel.
All of this is per sample, of course, which
means that the mid and side channels are what
actually passes through our LPC and residual
shenanigans.
The big advantage is now that the side channel
is usually very silent or, in fact, perfectly
silent.
Therefore, it can usually be compressed extremely
well, all in all amounting to not much more
than just compressed mono data.
And that’s it for today!
This is all that FLAC does to compress audio.
Let’s revisit what we learned today because
it’s a lot.
First, audio channels are decorrelated if
needed.
Then, we approximate a channel’s data with
linear predictive coding, and we’ll often
use a polynomial predictor.
We store the coefficients of the LPC as well
as the warm-up and treat the difference between
encoded and actual signal as the residual.
This residual is then encoded with an exponential
Golomb code of arbitrary order.
Here I want to end the second video.
You now understand all the theory behind FLAC’s
audio compression, but in the final video,
I want to look at how that works in practice.